<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortatyon or warnynge, to beware of greater plagues &amp; troubles, then are yet come vppon thys realme, for the synnes and wyckednes that hath bene, &amp; is yet dayly commytted there in..</title>
            <author>Coucheman, Giles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07535</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 76698335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5870.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S469843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">76698335</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 76698335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 2241:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortatyon or warnynge, to beware of greater plagues &amp; troubles, then are yet come vppon thys realme, for the synnes and wyckednes that hath bene, &amp; is yet dayly commytted there in..</title>
                  <author>Coucheman, Giles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[87] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in Paules Church yearde, at the sygne of the starre, by Thomas Raynalde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.L.I. [1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author attribution from prologue, p. [3].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks B³-B⁵, E⁶; stained, tightly bound with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatyon or Warnynge, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of greater plagues &amp; troubles, then are yet come vppon thys Realme, for the ſynnes and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes that hath bene, &amp; is yet dayly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted there in.</p>
            <p>M.D.LI.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Ieremye. xx.b.</bibl>
               <p>¶ All the daye longe am I deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laughed to ſcorne of euerye man, becauſe I haue now preached longe agaynſt malycyous tyranny, and ſhewed them of deſtruction, for the whych cauſe they caſt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of thee Lorde in my teeth, &amp; take me euer to the worſte.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>☞ Abacuc. i.</head>
            <p>O Lord how longe ſhal I crye, and thou wylte not heare, how longe ſhal I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne vnto thee, ſufferynge wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, &amp; thou wilt not help, why letteſt thou me ſe wery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; labour, tyranny &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ar before me, power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergoeth right, for the lawe is toarne in peces, &amp; ther can no ryght iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t go forth, and why? the vngodly is more ſette by then the righteous, this is thee cauſe that wronge iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:2"/>
            <head>The Prologue <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Gylis Coucheman to all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Readers vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this boke ſhal come, Wyſheth grace, mercye &amp; peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God the father of our Lorde Ieſus chriſte, wyth encreace of repentaunce and amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyfe thorow our Lord and onely Sauyour, &amp; by the workyng of the holy ſpyryte. Amen.</head>
            <p>LYke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almyghty eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal god of his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; loue, not onely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning after his own ſimilitude &amp; likenes, but alſo whan he was loſte, moſt graciouſly redemed hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; broughte hym out of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo whan ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarding his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful creation, nether his moſt deare redemption) gropethe in darckeneſſe, in vyce and
<pb facs="tcp:184229:3"/> blyndnes, lyeth in the deuils priſon, and goeth in the way of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacion, God alwayes ſetteth vp hys lighte before hym, ſendethe thee meſſage of hys worde vnto hym, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth him what caſe he is in, geueth hym warnynge, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the pryſon dore, calleth him out of the deuyls ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, telleth him what daunger it is to bee hys bondman, or ſeruaunte vnto ſynne. Thys doth God alwaye before he puniſhe &amp; plague the worlde. This (I ſay) hath euer ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of god ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, as the ſtories and Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes of al the holy Byble doeth teſtyfye.</p>
            <p>And thoughe we had no writinges of gods actes in times paſt, yet hath he prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed
<pb facs="tcp:184229:3"/> and vſed thys ſame his wonderfull worcke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vppon vs nowe in oure dayes, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyke as we muſte nedes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that we ar crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of god, &amp; redemed by his only mercy in hys deare ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus chriſt. So can we not denye, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue hearde his holy meſſage, had no leſſe preachinges &amp; warninges of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers to come, then other haue had before our dayes. Yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame merciful god that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Noe to preach righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe vnto thee wicked world, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuytes by his word in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the prophet Ionas, hath done eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion, &amp; ſome (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore) hath he brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght out of darknes into hys
<pb facs="tcp:184229:4"/> wonderful light &amp; out of the deuyls ſeruice into the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his moſt deare ſonne.</p>
            <p>But alas &amp; wo to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful world, for like as a great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that be in pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil not come forth wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ar called &amp; the dore ſet ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but go on ſtil ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in darknes whan the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of light is offred them.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo, yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> playe a wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s part, &amp; do as he is warned by gods worde, he ſhal haue a greate ſort,<note place="margin">Thei that forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thee vngodlye, but ſoche as kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrethe them, prou xxviii</note> yea a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of ſcornefull mockers (the whych becauſe the man wyl not daunce in the deuils morys with theym, nor kepe theyr company in the bonda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of ſynne &amp; vyce, neyther ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with them vnto like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſyon) that wyll laughe
<pb facs="tcp:184229:4"/> him to ſcorne &amp; mock him eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his face, &amp; lyke as whan a true poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh out of pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhal haue mo to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gaſing and gaping vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do him good, or to hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his fees, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo now, that god of his mercy hathe called ſome of vs out of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worldly wicked doers, my lordes fole w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs &amp; mocked vs, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe we ſit not ſtyl w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other pryſoners in ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; vice, ther goeth an apoſtle (ſayth one) ther goeth one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Foules ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that eſchu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth euyll. prou. xiii, c</note> ſayth another, ther go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, a iuſtifier of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf, ſaith another, ther goeth one that wyl lyue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſinne, ſayth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother, and thus is it come to paſſe that who ſo euer wil
<pb facs="tcp:184229:5"/> folowe Chriſt and hys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and forſake euyl in his lyfe &amp; conuerſation, he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſed &amp; hated of the world, &amp; alſo mocked &amp; ieſted vpon. But the diſciple is not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his maſter, nether the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte aboue hys lorde, for yf they haue called the good man of the houſholde Belza<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bub, how moche more ſhall they cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys houſhold ſo.<note place="margin">Yf I were a fleſhelye felowe &amp; a preacher of lyes &amp; tolde them that they myght ſyt bybbing &amp; bollynge &amp; be dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, o that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete for thys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Mich. ii. c</note> O Lord why doo men ſo moch mocke vs, &amp; ſcorne vs, for wel doyng, ſurely I can not tell, except it be for thys cauſe, that they be nothinge mynded to folowe chriſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, for yf they were, they wolde not do ſo.</p>
            <p>O Lord wher to is thys worlde come, for lyke as we had neade in tymes paſte to
<pb facs="tcp:184229:5"/> haue ſoch an Apoſtle as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly S. Paule was, to rebuke the vayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fydence that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd put in theyr worckes, &amp; to tell vs that no worke of our doyng, but fayth of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des workinge, doeth iuſtifie vs in hys ſyght.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo now, we had no leſſe nede of ſoch an Apoſtle as was holye S. Iames, to rebuke thys horrible vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefulnes of men, that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſinge them ſelues to be chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; to holde of Chriſtes old fayth, &amp; are yet dead vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al good worckes, receyue not the word of god in meke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, caſt not away al vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; maliciouſnes, but are ſwyft to ſpeake, to talcke, to iangle, &amp; to take diſpleaſure, and are forgetful hearers of
<pb facs="tcp:184229:6"/> thee worde and not lyuers there after boaſtynge theym ſelues to bee of gods pure &amp; vndefyled relygyon,<note place="margin">They ſay that they knowe god, but with theyr dedes they do denye hym. Titu. ii. c</note> and yet refrayne not theyr tongues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyl, viſet not the poore, the frendleſſe and thee deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in theyr trouble, nether kepe them ſelues vndefyled from thys worlde.</p>
            <p>What an occaſyon might ſoche an apoſtle (as holy S. Iames was) haue to wryte another, yea a more ſharper Epyſtle, ſeynge ſo manye pretendynge to be of Ieſus chriſtes olde faythe and rely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyon, and are yet ſo parcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and haue ſoche a carnall reſpecte of perſons, are not ryche in faythe, but deſpyſe thee poore, practyſe not thee lawe of godly loue, talcke &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:184229:6"/> Iangle of faythe not hauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the worckes therof, cloth not thee naked, helpe not the poore too theyr ryghte, nor regarde not theyr neceſſyte, haue but a deade faythe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not by good and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worckes the true and olde faythe of Chriſt, and are but vayne beleuers, haue not the effections workyng &amp; lyuing fayth that Abraham had.</p>
            <p>Howe wold holy Saynt Iames reproue theſe bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vp of ſtraunge doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; falſe opynyons, theſe blaſphemers, backbyters, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyers of good men, falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of goddes trueth, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers wyth the ſame, ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye fyre (as they ſaye) wythe one hande, and water in the other, prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to be lerned
<pb facs="tcp:184229:7"/> and yet bryng not forthe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worckes of good conuerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion in mekenes out of god wyſdome, but in froward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, and oute of carnal doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne, are churlyſſhe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vneaſye to be intreated.</p>
            <p>Wherefore moſte dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Readers, who ſo euer of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hathe bene ſlacke to folowe thee good lyfe and Godlye conuerſatyon that Sayncte Iames (and all thee holye ſcrypture beſydes) requyreth to bee in theym whyche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thee holye relygyon of oure ſauyoure Chriſte, lette hym nowe take better hold, turne agayne to thee truth, And folowe that louynge exhortacyon whyche holye S. Iames makethe in thee latter ende of hys Epyſtle,<note place="margin">Iame. v. b</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:184229:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> and lette vs that haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed thee holye relygyon of Chryſte in dede (not onelye bee contente too abyde anye ſtorme or trouble for it, or to bee mocked, ſcorned, and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted, yea and put to death therfore, yf it ſo pleaſe god) but alſo euerye one of vs to hys power, in hys harte by feruent prayer, in his mouth by good woordes, and in all hys bodye by vertuous conuerſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and good Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyan workes, helpe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure that thee bleſſed word of god, maye haue thee due honoure belongynge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and that the ſame whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it hathe loſte thorowe the vngodly behauiour of ſo me, may thorowe thee grace and goodneſſe of God bee
<pb facs="tcp:184229:8"/> wonne agayne in oure goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyuing, that god maye hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vs better ſeruauntes, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prince true ſubiectes, &amp; ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neyghbours more vnfayned louers, then many haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before vs.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <head>¶ The Prologue to the Miniſters.</head>
            <p>ANd now to al you tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue taken the name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paſtours, ſhepeherdes and leaders of thee flockes (as ye wold be called) as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth as I can iudge of you, ye are the greateſte cauſe of the vnthankefull receauinge of the woorde of God, and that thee people walcke ſo
<pb facs="tcp:184229:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> carnallye and ſo laſciuiouſly as they doo, for ye your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues walcke ſo broade and ſo farre wyde from the trueth of the goſpel, that the verye babes can ſpye it in you, yea and thee verye papyſtes that be enemyes to thee Goſpell alſo. For they ſaye: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde theyr lyuynges &amp; how they goo theym ſelues that ſhoulde be thee ſhewe token too all theyr flockes (ſaye they) marcke theyr wyues alſo (ſaye they) how trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melye they be decked of the newe faſſhyon, wyth theyr hayre layde abroade, hauyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge on gorgyouſe apparell, as mynyuere cappes, french hoodes, Frockes, and Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſockes garded, ſtytched, and brodered wyth lace, yea and
<pb facs="tcp:184229:9"/> rynges vpon theyr fyngers more lyke ladyes and gentyl wemen, then thee wyues of myniſters (ſay they) yea clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne contrary and agaynſt the doctrine of S. peter and S. Paul alſo,<note place="margin">i, pet. iii a i, tim ii. b</note> as ye ful wel kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we by theyr Epyſtles. But ſurely I maruayle howe ye dare take vppon you to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſeing that ye can not (or wyll not) teache nor rule youre owne ſelues and youre wyues.</p>
            <p>But it is lytle maruayle in dede conſyderynge what ye ſeke in youre teachynge and the ſtate that ye walcke in and the porte that ye bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,<note place="margin">O ye prye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes ye tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che for lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, o ye prophetes ye prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye for mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney. mych. iii. c</note> for it wyll not bee mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned wythe a lytle, and therefore ye hadde nede of that ye ſeke (whych is I fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re)
<pb facs="tcp:184229:9"/> greate rewardes and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te lyuynges for youre do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges too mayntayne youre pryde wythall, or elles it wyll not holde longe, and than al youre glorye is loſte in thys worlde. But ye oughte to ſeke goddes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory only and not your owne.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ye doo not ſo. Therefore thus ſayethe thee Lorde.<note place="margin">Ezechiel xxxiiii, a</note> Wo bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you ſhepheardes, that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de youre ſelues. Shoulde not thee ſhepheardes fede theyr flockes (ſayethe thee Lorde) but ye haue eaten vp thee fatte, ye haue clothed youre ſelues, wyth the wol, thee beſte fedde haue ye ſlai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but thee flockes haue ye not noryſhed, the weke haue
<pb facs="tcp:184229:10"/> ye not holden vp, thee ſycke haue ye not healed, thee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken haue ye not bounde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, thee oute caſtes haue ye not broughte agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, thee loſte haue ye not ſoughte, but churlyſſhelye and cruellye haue ye ruled theym (ſayethe thee Lorde) yea, ye haue eaten vppe thee ſynnes of thee people (as thee Prophete ſayethe) and haue coraged them in theyr wyckedneſſe and thus all ye Pryeſtes are become lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee people (or rather worſe I feare),<note place="margin">Oſe. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i, b</note> for where ſhall ye haue a pryeſte in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye paryſſhe but he is geuen too one vayne thynge or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">They take the moſte ſhamefull men by the hand flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not returne from theyr ſynnes. Ier xxiii b</note> eyther to ſhotyng bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, hawkynge, huntyng, cardynge, dyceſynge, quayt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:10"/> loggettynge, peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prycke, tables, or one vayne paſtyme or other, ye or elſe a tauerne haunter or a good companyon (as they call theym) whych is cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to the rule of Saynt Paule, whyche ſayeth that thee mynyſters muſte be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte,<note place="margin">i. tim. iii. b</note> and not double ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, not geuen too moche wyne, neyther too fylthye lucre, but hauynge the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of faythe in pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence, and lette theym fyrſte bee proued and then lette theym mynyſter (ſayeth he) yf they bee founde bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleſſe, euen ſo muſte theyr wyues bee honeſte, not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll ſpeakers, but ſober and faythfull in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:11"/>
            <p>O Lorde, yf we ſhoulde haue no mynyſters wythe in thys Realme excepte we ſhoulde fyrſte proue theym and fynde theym faultles ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge too thee rule of S. Paule, I doute we ſhoulde fynde very fewe that is mete for thee offyce, thee more is thee pytye that it is not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loked vnto, by thee Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes, who hathe the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryte geuen vnto theym of thee hygher power, of thee choſynge and prouynge of theym before they come too thee offyce, for thee pryeſtes lyppes ſhoulde bee ſure of knowledge (ſayth the lorde) than menne maye ſeke thee lawe at hys mouthe,<note place="margin">Malac. ii,</note> for he is a meſſenger of the Lorde of hoſtes. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:11"/>
            <p>neceſſary to the bodye. So that on bothe partyes loue ſhalbe ſought, &amp; the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations wylbe edifyed &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, &amp; god thorowe you ſhall be prayſed. And that it maye thus come to paſſe lett vs all praye wyth one hart &amp; one mynde that we maye ther to agre to ſaye.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:12"/>
            <head>An Exhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or warning, to bewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of greater plagues &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles, then are yet come vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thys Realme, for the ſynne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; wickednes that hath bene and is yet dayly commytte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therin.</head>
            <p>GRace, mercy and peace from Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the father of our Lord Ieſus chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte, with increaſe of knowledge in his holy &amp; euerlaſting word, be with al thoſe that profeſſe Chriſte &amp; take hym to be their only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; redemer (the whych knowledge in his holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, I praye too God that it may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; alter theyr ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:184229:12"/> ſo, that wher as thei we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wont to talke &amp; ſpeake of Chriſte in wordes) that they nay now preach him in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yues &amp; conuerſation.<note place="margin">He that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitteth ſinne, is of the deuyll i. Io, iii. b</note> For what a greate ſhame is it to vs, that take chriſt to be oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auiour &amp; mayſter (whereof we take our names &amp; are cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led chriſtians) &amp; profeſſe him in wordes (as S. paul ſaith) and wyl denie him in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.<note place="margin">Titum. i. c</note> For what ſoeuer oure wordes &amp; talkes be, it is our lyues &amp; worckes that decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth whoſe diſciples we are, and therfore ſaith S. Iohn,<note place="margin">i. Io. iii. b</note> by this ar the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god knowen, &amp; the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuyl. Therfore deare &amp; wel beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre what ye haue profeſſed in your bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me (you, &amp; your parentes for
<pb facs="tcp:184229:13"/> you) remembre I ſaye how that you haue promyſed to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forſake the deuyl and al hys workes &amp; to cleue vnto chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and do his wil &amp; worckes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to become a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in chriſt and to fyght manfully wyth hym agaynſte the deuyll the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world &amp; the fleſh, &amp; to folow hym in lyfe &amp; conuerſation. Now my brethren ye know what a promiſe that is made betwene man &amp; man, &amp; howe that promiſe that is made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man ought to be kept &amp; not broken, &amp; yf it fortune too be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ye know what a dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to the world ther lyeth on it. Now yf the promyſe made with man ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to be kept vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne of a dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Know ye therfore my brethren that the promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whych is made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:13"/> ought moch more to be kept &amp; not broken vnder the daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger of eternal condempnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ye haue promyſed alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o fyghte agaynſt the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; your owne fleſhe. Now yf ye geue ouer youre ſelues to ſerue both the worlde and your owne luſtes and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alſo, how do ye fyghte (thincke you), knowe ye not (ſayth S. paul) that to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer ye geue ouer your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to ſerue,<note place="margin">Rom vi. b Ioh, viii, c ii pet ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> his ſeruauntes ye are to whom ſoeuer ye do obeye, whether it be of ſynne vnto deathe, or of obedience vnto righteouſnes. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dearlye beloued be ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemye do not deceaue you as he deceaued Eua, making you beleue that you maye do what you wyll, &amp; yet pleaſe god. Be not deceiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:14"/> For yf ye do that whyche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſynne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar ye the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſynne, &amp; ye know that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rewarde of ſynne is death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condempnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yf ye d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which is good in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of god, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at ye ſure that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be the chyldren of God. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye muſte be ſure that the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie make ye not beleue that to be good whyche is euyll, therfore trye youre worckes wyth gods word,<note place="margin">pſa. cxviii</note> as Dauid ſayth. Lord thy word is a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne vnto my fete, &amp; a lyght vnto my pathes, therefore what ſoeuer worke it be trie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it by gods word, &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word wyl alowe it to be good, do it, yf not, then do it not how holy or good ſoeuer it ſeme to be in your owne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For it maketh me lamente in my harte to ſee howe the
<pb facs="tcp:184229:14"/> world is deceiued by the ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teltye of the enemye, in cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them away ſo, in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte of vaine thinges of this worlde, for a greate manye there bee that profeſſe chriſte and his relygyon, and yet do walcke ſo carnalli and ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuiouſly at large, as though ther were no law nether yet god, yea verely they be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnto the goſpel of god, whoſe ende, bee ye ſure, is dampnacion, and their glory ſhall be to their owne ſhame they are ſo carnally mynded &amp; wyl not ſtryue agaynſte it, yea &amp; yet who ſoeuer ſhulde be ſo bold to ſay vnto theym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were not of god, they wold ſurely deny it and ſay, yes, for I am chriſtened and therfore am I of god as wel as you (as though al laye in
<pb facs="tcp:184229:15"/> receyuyng of baptyme only)</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Titum, i, c</note>And theſe be they that S Paule ſpeaketh of, ſayinge they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe wyth their mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes that they know god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be hys ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">Thee fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes ſaye in their hartes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſhe ther is no god. pſal. xiii, a</note> but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their dedes they do deny him &amp; be none of his, for ſo moch as they are abhomynable i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their doynges and vnto all good workes diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable.</p>
            <p>And ther is another ſort al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo whyche walkethe not ſo broade outwardly, but hath a ſhew like vnto holines, but they are (as chriſt ſayth) lyke vnto a painted ſupulcre whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſheweth fayre and bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull outwarde,<note place="margin">math, xxiii d,</note> but within they are ful of dead mennes bones and all fylthynes. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo are they, for they wyl ſhewe theym ſelues very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye at thee churche and elſe
<pb facs="tcp:184229:15"/> wher, but whan ye ſhal haue any thyng to do wyth them, ye ſhall fynde theym full of malyce and al kynde of wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes with in, proue theym whan ye wyll and ye ſhall fynde theym euen ſoche peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as it wold lamente anye chryſten harte to ſe it. For yf they goo to the churche and there ſaye and number a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn praiers after their own ymagynacion, &amp; ther to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and ſe certayn ceremonies mynyſtred, they thynke to be ſafe all that daye &amp; maye do what they lyſt, or to bie &amp; ſel &amp; begyle &amp; deceyue the poore and ſymple people, yea and to ſyt and ſpende the tyme at tables and cardes or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vaine paſtime al the day after, &amp; there to ſyt &amp; ſweare &amp; talke vaine &amp; ydle wordes,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:16"/> &amp; do not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that chriſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayth that they ſhall geue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptes of euery ydle word that they ſpeake at the daye of Iudgemente,<note place="margin">mat. xii. d</note> and yet be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydes that yf ye doo ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, or ſpeake againſt their doynges ye ſhall fynde that they wyll not bee pleaſed (no not ſcarſe wyth bloud), and is not thys a myſerable blyndnes caſte vppon theym of the enemye, thyncke you, that they ſhal ſeme to theym ſelues to be ſo holye and ſo wel for vſynge this trade of lyfe outward, whan there is nothyng well wythin, for yf they wold trye theym ſelues by goddes word (as is ſayde before) they ſhuld fynd them ſelues farre from the lyfe of a chryſtyan of Chriſte, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſerpent hath ſo deceiued
<pb facs="tcp:184229:16"/> theym that they bee at peace wyth them ſelues and nede nothyng to do more, but to kepe thys outewarde trade of lyfe.</p>
            <p>Alſo they thinke to winne heauen by the folowynge of the olde law, &amp; in kepyng of the outward ſacramentes &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eremonies therof. But yf ye axe them the ſygnyficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ſacrament and thee promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes annyxed to them,<note place="margin">How can they haue vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng that are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, pſalm lii. a.</note> or of a ceremonye, they can not tell what it meanethe, but ſaye, hath no god lefte them for vs too kepe and obſerue, what nede we any more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes or ſygnyfycatyons.</p>
            <p>O thou ſuttyll enemye full well knoweſt thou that thee outwarde worke wythoute the promys as litle profiteth theym as doeth the ſygne at
<pb facs="tcp:184229:17"/> the tauernes dore to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be a thyrſte, whan ther is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wyne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in to be had. And ye wyl they ſeke theyr iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon in the outwarde work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof onely.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">ii, ii, iii, a,</note>And this is the cauſe (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the apoſtle ſayth) euery on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is become a pryuate louer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them ſelues, and not of they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neyghbours. And how do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they loue them ſelues (thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you),<note place="margin">After this maner doeth thee worldin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues</note> verely they ar become couetous, boſters, proud, cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed ſpeakers, diſobedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fathers and mothers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull, vnholye, churlyſhe, ſtubborne, falſe accuſers, ria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours, fearſe, diſpiſers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are good, traitoures, heddie, hie mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, gredy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voluptuouſnes more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the louers of god, hauing a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litude of godly lyuynge, but
<pb facs="tcp:184229:17"/> haue denied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power therof, but ſoche abhorre ſayth S. paul, O lord what a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world is this, whan the people bee in thys caſe that they haue no feare of god be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore their eies, but think that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey be in good ſtate of liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei liue thus farre wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the goſpell &amp; doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to loue our neyghbors as our own ſelf &amp; ſeke their welth &amp; edy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyinge to theyr comforte.<note place="margin">We are bounde to loue god wyth all our hartes &amp; powers and oure neighbors as oure ſelf, and ſo is all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe &amp; the prophetes fulfylled. mat, xxii. d</note>
            </p>
            <p>But the wicked worldlin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ar in this mind now (the lord geue them grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente and amende it) that yf they maye haue all thynges at theyr wyl &amp; pleaſure, they care not although the poore nedy neighbor ſterue &amp; be in lack or peryſhe in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:184229:18"/> whyle, for they ſaye, yf I be wel clothed &amp; warme, what care I who goethe naked &amp; ſuffre colde, yf I bee wel fed with the beſt and fineſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and lack none, what care I who is an hungred and peryſh for lacke of the worſt meate, yf I bee well couered wythe a fayre houſe gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye decte and in all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes trymmed with the beſte, what care I who dwelleth in a houſe vncouered rainyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in, in euery corner, ſpyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng and deſtroying all that he hath, and the houſe lyke to fall downe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head, yf I may ſyt warme and at eaſe and at reſte, takinge no payne, hauinge money ynou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe and all thinge broughte home too me, what care I who is colde, takyng pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne
<pb facs="tcp:184229:18"/> and haue noo reſte nor eaſe, nyght nor daye, lacking mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney &amp; al thing that ſhuld do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good, yf I may haue my rentes and farme broughte home to me wythout any ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, what care I though the farmers care &amp; ſtudye nyght and day, hauing nether coat nor cloke to couer hym, hys wyfe or his children withal, no nor yet eat a good meales meat in a yere. Thus farre is the loue of the worlde gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of god, that they care not one for another, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder that we al ſhuld be membres of one body. Yf they dyd remember that we were al members of one bodye, I thinke verelye that natural loue wold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them indifferently one to care for another, and one to
<pb facs="tcp:184229:19"/> loue another, al though the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, nether in the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor yet in the new.</p>
            <p>For this we al know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of one body be ſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited &amp; knyt in loue together to the body,<note place="margin">The righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous wyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, but the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Prou, xxix</note> that yf one mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber fortune to take hurte or harme al the reſt ſuffer paine &amp; grief w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym, or yf one me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be had in honor, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt is glad &amp; reioyce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, ſoch is the loue that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the body. Therfore for hys ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyed to redeme vs al (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I ſay) &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that we al be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers (or ſhuld be) to one head, whych is chriſte, &amp; that we do now awake out of ſynne &amp; caſt awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs the clokes of diſhoneſtie and become louers of god in his
<pb facs="tcp:184229:19"/> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, &amp; knowe that what ſoeuer ye doo to one of thee leaſte of theſe my brethren (ſayth Chriſte) ye do it vnto me. Remembre this that our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth thus his owne ſelf alſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat who ſoeuer geueth to one of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe lyttle ones a cup of colde water in my name, I tel you ſayth he, he ſhal not loſe his reward Now yf this lyttle loue ſhewed vnto one of his creatures ſhall not be vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, be ye ſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moche more ſhal the wrong &amp; iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vnto condempnation.</p>
            <p>Yet once agayne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſaye, remember thys vnfayned loue that thee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God hadde vnto the whole worlde. Yea hys loue was ſo great towardes ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynd
<pb facs="tcp:184229:20"/> (beyng yet his enemie) that he gaue his only &amp; dear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to the death, to redeme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage &amp; thraldo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuyll. O what coulde he doo more for vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to geue thys ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate &amp; vnſpotted lambe for vs, &amp; to vs, that who ſo euer now wyll repent of the lyfe that is paſt, &amp; beleue &amp; truſte onli in him, he ſhal be ſure to be ſaued for hys ſake, ſo he continue to the ende. And he requyreth nothing ſo moche of vs as to loue one a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other, yea by thys loue (ſayeth he) ſhal al men know that ye are my diſciples. Now to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, yf we loue not one ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, then is it a playne caſe that we be none of hys, ſaye what we wyll, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of god ſtandeth not in
<pb facs="tcp:184229:20"/> wordes, but in power, for lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue is the fulfylling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole lawe. Yea he hath not onely geuen vnto vs this Ieſus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo al thinges wyth hym, yea he hath geuen vs his eternal and euerlaſting worde to be our comfort, to rule &amp; to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne our liues by, &amp; to ſhew vs all the good wyll of oure heauenlye father towardes vs, in &amp; for Ieſus chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Yea what more coulde he haue done, that he hathe not done for vs.</p>
            <p>But now, yf he loke amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſte vs for equyte, he ſhall fynd in ſtede of equyte, wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. And yf he loke for righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, he ſhall haue vs full of myſery &amp; wretchednes (as the Prophete ſayeth) for the more good he doeth vnto vs<note place="margin">Eſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:184229:21"/> &amp; thee more he increaſeth vs with his giftes &amp; benefytes, the more we go aſtray wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tonly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; prouoke him vnto wrath w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our owne y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, vayne &amp; mad inuentions for as it is wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whan va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie &amp; ydlenes getteth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerhand among the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men,<note place="margin">Pſal, xl,</note> al are ful of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge the more we receaue of him, the more we ought to be thanke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full vnto him for it, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more we ſhuld be ſtudious &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to beſtowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; glory, ſeking alwayes his honour and prayſe. And not to beſtow them to fulfyl our owne fylthy &amp; carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre. Saying to our ſelues &amp; to other, that they be ours &amp; may do with them what we wyll, &amp; ſo deceaue our owne
<pb facs="tcp:184229:21"/> ſelues, &amp; beſtow them about vayne vanitie. Yea, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme aboute that whyche is wycked &amp; dampnable in the ſyght of God. As to beſtow them aboute harlottes, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, dyce, tables, bowles and ſoche lyke wycked abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon, for the which we do not onely offend the eternal God for ſo beſtowynge of them, but alſo greately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him vnto wrath agayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte vs, for ſo myſuſynge and conſumynge thee tyme that is ſpente about them, alſo yf we beſtow them about ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes in buildinges, gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſnes in rayment, &amp; alſo in delicious fare, more then nede requyreth, we do great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly offend therin. And therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re for the loue of god conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with your ſelues &amp; know
<pb facs="tcp:184229:22"/> for a ſuerty, that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryches and goodes that anye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth at the hand of god, they are but delyuered vnto you &amp; lente you for a while, and ye made ſtewardes of them to beſtowe them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the wyl of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, and not to our owne wyl, except our wil be al together let to prefar and ſet forth gods wil, for yf we beſtow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as is afore ſayd, we ſhal ſurely rendre a ſtray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accomptes for the vtmooſte iote of theim. And not onely for theſe temporall gyftes, but alſo wee ſhall rendre a ſtrayte accomptes for all the ſpiritual giftes that we haue receaued of god, as wyſdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge, fayth, healyng, prophecyinge, iudgementes of ſpirites. &amp;c. Yf we beſtow
<pb facs="tcp:184229:22"/> them not to goddes honour and glory and to our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours welth and comfort.</p>
            <p>Wel beloued in our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt I wold ye ſhulde not thynke that I haue ſayd al thys as a teacher, but as a poore litle membre of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me body that ye ar of, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge you &amp; puttynge you in remembraunce not onelye of the manyfold gyftes &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of our eternal father to vs warde in tymes paſt, but alſo now in this time eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, knowing and ſeyng the world ſo full of all kynde of wyckednes &amp; miſery, and ſo vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull as they be, ye eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thoughe there were no god. Wherfore I praye you conſider w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſelues, and note wel the ſinnes of Sodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Gomora and way the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel
<pb facs="tcp:184229:23"/> in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſinnes of this Realme &amp; ye ſhal fynd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I feare me (not onli mo) but alſo a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te deale wors. And wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re do I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wors, think you, verely, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> god hath geuen vnto vs his only ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by &amp; in whom we are called Chriſtyans, &amp; yet we lyue ſo Heathen lyke that it wyll be double dampnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, yea &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs al thinges ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſlye, &amp; alſo hath left vnto vs his holy &amp; ſacred word amonge vs for our comfort (yea and not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thys only) but alſo he hathe not ceaſed nyght nor day to crie vnto vs by his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the prophetes &amp; myniſters of hys goſpell, that we ſhulde euerye one of vs turne from his ſynnes repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and become
<pb facs="tcp:184229:23"/> the folowers of him in loue, but we wyll not, but are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lyke vnto the defe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſtoppethe her eares that ſhe ſhulde not heare the voyce of thee charmers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he charme neuer ſo wiſely. Euen ſoch ar we,<note place="margin">As for the warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s they take it but for wynde, Iere, v, b,</note> for we wyl not heare, nor do af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the preachers of goddes word although thei preach &amp; teach neuer ſo wel or ſo wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i, yea, preach they what thei wyl or what they can, it wyl not ſerue, no nor yet helpe. We ar content to alow it in wordes and to ſay well by it, but to folowe it in life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatyon (in reſpecte of the multitude) ther is none that wyl do it, or very few, for I thynke verely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, yf Sodome &amp; Gomorra had, had Gods word ſo plenteouſly among
<pb facs="tcp:184229:24"/> them as we haue had and ſo longe, &amp; ſo moch preachyng againſt ſinne, they wold ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly a repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in ſackcloth and aſſhes. And for thys cauſe I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of Sodom &amp; Gomorra For the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of Sodome &amp; Gomorra were theſe, pryde, fulnes of meat,<note place="margin">The ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doma and Gomorra. Eze. xvi. e</note> abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce &amp; ydlenes, beſydes that they reched not their hande to the poore &amp; nedy, and whyche of theſe lackethe here in thys Realme think you, I trowe none of them al, beſydes the ouerplus of other. For who ſawe euer ſo moche pryde in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> women &amp; children as ther is now, ſo moche ſuperfluyte in meates &amp; drinkes, ſo moch abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce of al thinges vp on earth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men as there is now, for ther is nothing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184229:24"/> men can deſyre but they may haue it for money. And who did euer ſe ſo many geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yue ydelye as they be now, &amp; I thinke verely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther was neuer ſo litle charite ſhewed vnto thee poore as there is now. And this is the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uery one ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth forth in his ſinnes as a wild hors in a bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tail (as the prophet ſaith) not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oking be hynd him,<note place="margin">Ier. viii. b</note> nor fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of god whyche is lyke to come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them for thys myſerable ſtate of lyfe that we now lyue in.</p>
            <p>For who is he amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs that now wil make his life &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation to agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys worde of lyfe, nay, rather a great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber wil make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a cloke for their ſinne and wickednes,<note place="margin">Brethren ye are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bertye, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye let not your liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye be an occatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the fleſſhe but by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſerue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Gal. v.a, Rom, viii</note> &amp; to ſerch dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for ſoch places in ſcripture
<pb facs="tcp:184229:25"/> (as they ſuppoſe) as ſhall maintaine them in al kynd of lybertye of the fleſhe, and do not remember that S. Paul fayth to be fleſhly mynded is death, but to be ſpirituallye minded is life &amp; peace, for the fleſhely or carnal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not pleaſe god (ſayeth he) but is thee enemye of God, ſeynge that the fleſhe is not ſubdued vnto the law of god.</p>
            <p>For is not this a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble thing to thynke &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber how longe we haue had this word &amp; goſpel of lyfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs, and how lytle i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath preuayled among vs, &amp; how few it hath wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of chryſt. O lord wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtonie harte wolde not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; lamente in hys harte to thyncke vpon thys: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184229:25"/> cal vs to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes, how lytle we haue wonne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys our talente hauing it ſo long as we haue had it in vſe &amp; occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying. I praye to god it bee not ſayd vnto vs, as it was ſaid vnto the euyl and ſlouth full ſeruaunte that S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">mat. xxv, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (ſayinge) thou euyl &amp; ſlouthful ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t kneweſt thou that I reaped wher I ſowed not, &amp; gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red where I ſtrowed not, thou ſhuldeſt therfore haue put my money to exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at my comming ſhulde I haue receiued mine owne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vantage. Therfore take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent from him &amp; geue it vnto him that hath .x. tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes (ſaid the lord) for who to hath, to him ſhall be geuen &amp; he ſhal haue aboundaunce, but who ſo hath not from him ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:184229:26"/> taken away eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he hath, and caſte thee vnprofytable ſeruaunte into vtter darcke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">This wyl be our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pente.</note> there ſhall be waylynge and gnaſhyng of teeth.</p>
            <p>For thys I ſay &amp; know it to be true that there is none w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this Realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to god therfore) that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtly ſay &amp; approue it to be true, but that he hath &amp; maye both heare &amp; reade the word of lyfe (yf he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther heare or reade) &amp; therfore ar we al wythout excuſe to god ward. Yea yf he do now pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vs &amp; take from vs this word of life &amp; geue it vnto a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother nacyon whyche was not worthye of it, and leaue vs cleane voyde &amp; emptye. Yea &amp; of al his promiſes &amp; al ſo of his good giftes &amp; bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites beſydes: We ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſay
<pb facs="tcp:184229:26"/> naye, but that we haue right wel deſerued it. Yea &amp; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ye ſhall beleue me thee better in this behalfe, I wyll aledge the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profyte that S. Paule bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in agaynſt the Romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame purpoſe (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge) haue they not hearde (ſaith he) yes,<note place="margin">pſ. xviii, a Roma. x. c</note> no doubt their ſound went out into all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; theyr wordes into the endes of the worlde. Howe thinke ye now, who can excu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe hym ſelfe vngiltie in thee knowledge of gods wordes and promyſes. Yf he now pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhe vs as we haue well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or is able to laye any thing to his charge or to abide his wrath. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I wyſhe &amp; deſyre in my harte, that euerye one of vs may yet now repent betimes
<pb facs="tcp:184229:27"/> and cal for mercy of him that hadde pytie of the Niniuites wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at the ſhort warning of one poore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.<note place="margin">Iona, iii b</note> Now ye do know that we haue had many mo than one to geue vs warninge (yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold help) ſince the goſpel came i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to this realme of Ing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land. For do ye not knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the nature &amp; propertie of god, yea, &amp; his old wont ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to geue warninge or he puniſh or plague the people. For he ſaith by his Prophet Amos,<note place="margin">amos, iii b</note> now doeth the Lord god no maner of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but he telleth his ſecrete before vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes,<note place="margin">The Lord god is ful of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; merci, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng great in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; truth pſ, lxxx v. c</note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roareth who wyl not be afrayd (ſaith he) ſeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth who wil not prophecy. As who ſhuld ſay, yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde
<pb facs="tcp:184229:27"/> byd any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue warning &amp; ſhew the people of theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, how dare he hold his to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gue but tel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes &amp; wickednes. Now truely I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre me, of ani peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple that euer hath ben ſence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord dyd pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gue, puniſh or deſtroy but he firſt gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before</p>
            <p>For,<note place="margin">Gene, vi, a i. Pet, iii e</note> before he deſtroyed al the hole erth by the great floud, he ſayd: my ſpyryt ſhal not alwaye ſtryue with man for he is but fleſſhe alſo, I wyl geue him reſpyt an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth &amp; twentye yeares. But after that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord ſaw that the wyckedneſſe of man was increaſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth &amp; that al the thought &amp; yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of theyr harte was but only euyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, it re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pented hym that he hadde
<pb facs="tcp:184229:28"/> made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, &amp; he ſorowed in his hart, &amp; ſayde: I wyl deſtroy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, both ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beaſt, worme &amp; fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le vnder the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for it repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth me that I made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O note thys well I praye you,<note place="margin">Note this</note> how the lord ſorowed in his hart (ſayth the texte) thincke you that he was not loth to deſtroye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had made. Yes verely. But whan he had lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked downe vpon the earth &amp; ſaw that it was corrupt, for al fleſhe had corrupt his way vpon earth, ſayth the text, it gaue hym occaſion for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye it. Then ſayd he vnto Noe his righteous ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ende of all fleſhe is come before me, for the yearth is full of miſchefe before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; lo, I wyl deſtroye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:184229:28"/> earth, wherfore make the an Arke wherin thou &amp; thy chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſaue your ſelues, for lo, I wil bringe a floude of water vpon the earth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all fleſſhe, wherein the breth of life is, but with the, wyl I make a couenaunte &amp; thou ſhalt go into the Arcke with thy ſonnes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy wife &amp; with thy ſonnes wyues. &amp;c Lo, here doth the lord make a couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wyth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Gen. xix, c Gene. v. d</note> for Noe was a ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; perfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; led a god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly lyfe in his tyme. And all thoſe that lyue righteouſlye &amp; godly as he dyd, the lorde doeth make alſo a couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te with them to preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Ieſus chriſtes ſake (not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the erth) but alſo preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting lyfe.<note place="margin">Leu, xviii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a pſa, xxxiii. and .xxxv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i. tim, iiii b Ezec, xx. b Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. b</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:29"/>
            <p>Here in is the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the righteous and the vnrighteous. For the righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe Noe was warned by god, &amp; he toke it for a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and dyd make prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordinge to the wordes of God and was preſerued. But the vngodly did not ſo, and therfore was deſtroyed, wherfore my deare &amp; welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our ſauiour chriſt I beſeche you be warned in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, leaſt the lord deſtroy you lykewyſe from the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ge. xviii, c</note>Alſo whan the lord was minded to deſtroy Sodoma &amp; Gomorra, &amp; was goynge thetherwarde for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe, he ſayd, how can I hyd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abraham the thinge that I wyll do, ſeynge he ſhall be a great &amp; myghty people, and all the people vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth
<pb facs="tcp:184229:29"/> ſhall be bleſſed in hym, for I know (ſayd the lord) that he wyl commaund his children and hys houſhold after him to kepe the way of the lord,<note place="margin">Note this well all ye that haue chyldren &amp; kepe houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde.</note> and to do after ryght &amp; conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience that thee Lorde maye bryng vpon Abraham what he hath promyſed hym. And the Lord ſayd: ther is a crye at Sodoma and Gomorra whych is great, &amp; theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes are exceading greuous,<note place="margin">Eze. xvi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> therefore wyll I go downe and ſee whether they haue done all together according to that crye whyche is come before me, or not, that I may know.<note place="margin">Ge. xviii, d</note> But Abraham reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord concernynge that matter in ſo moch that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord promiſed him, yf there were fyftye ryghteous w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie, he wold ſaue al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt
<pb facs="tcp:184229:30"/> for thoſe fyftyes ſakes, but he left hym not ſo, ſeinge he was ſo merciful a Lorde to graunt him his requeſte, he aſked him yf there were but xlv. in that place, yf he wold deſtroy the hole citie for lack of thoſe fyue, he ſayde: yf I fynde but .xlv. therin I wyll not deſtroy them, but he left him not ſo nether, but reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned further in that behalf, &amp; ſayd, yf ther be but .xl. and ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xl. to thyrtie, &amp; to .xx. &amp; ſo to ten, but ther could not ten be found therin, wherfore al the reſt periſhed,<note place="margin">Gene. xix.</note> ſaue iuſt lot and his wife &amp; his two dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghters. For the meſſengers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were ſent for to deſtroy the cytie, ſaid vnto lot, haſt thou yet here any ſonne in law, or ſonnes or doughters, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto the (ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:184229:30"/> they) bryng them out of this place, for we muſte deſtroye thys place, becauſe thee crye of them is greate before the lord, which hath ſente vs to deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then wente Lot forth &amp; ſpake to his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in law (which ſhuld haue mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his daughters) &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warning, &amp; ſaid, O ſtand vp &amp; get you out of thys place, for the lord wyl deſtroy this cytie. Neuertheles they toke it but for a ſport and wolde not beleue hys ſaying, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they peryſhed wyth the reſte, as I feare me, we of thys Realme are lyke to do yf we wyll not bee warned in tyme, for thus is it wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Prophete as folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth after, but it may wel be ſayde vnto vs nowe in thys Realme the more is the pitie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:31"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iere, vii, c</note>Thus ſayeth the lorde of hoſtes the god of Iſrael, ye heape vp your burnt offrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſacrifices &amp; eate the fleſh, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I brought your fathers out of Egipt, I ſpake no wordes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of burnt offrynges &amp; ſacrifyces, but this I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; obey my voyce &amp; I wil be your god &amp; ye ſhall be my people, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye walk in al the wayes which I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.<note place="margin">Exod, ix. a</note> 
               <note place="margin">☞</note> But thei were not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, no more ar we, they incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not their eares therunto, no more do we, but we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after their owne ymaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nacyons of their owne wicked hart. And euen ſo do we or rather wors &amp; yf it be poſſyble. And ſo they turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues away &amp; conuerted not vnto me (ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde) &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:184229:31"/> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do we turne our ſelues away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our own ymaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">We ar ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the deef adder that ſcoppeth her eares y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ſhulde not heare the voyce of the char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, Pſal. lvii, a, and Actu. vii, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſome with one thyng &amp; ſome with another, ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cardes, ſome wythe dice, ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tables, ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bowles, ſome with ſhoting, ſome with dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyng, ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, ſome with hawking, ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hoore hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting &amp; ſome with gay clothing of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faſhion, al becut &amp; be pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed more like Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people or players, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that doth profeſſe the holy re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt, for we wil not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert vnto the lord withall our hart. And this haue they done fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time that youre fathers came oute of Egipte vnto this day (ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo haue we done euer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the time that we were firſt brought out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of the
<pb facs="tcp:184229:32"/> Biſhop of Rome by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lighte of the goſpell.<note place="margin">Ierem. vii and .xxv. and, xxix</note> Neuertheles I ſent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes all the prophetes (ſayeth the lord) &amp; euen ſo hath he done vnto vs, I roſe vp early (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the lord) &amp; ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worde, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hath he done vnto vs, yet wold thei not herken, no more wyll we, nor offer me theyr eares, no more wil we, but were obſtynate &amp; worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr fathers (ſayth the lord) &amp; euen ſo be we, &amp; thou ſhalte nowe ſpeake all theſe wordes vnto them, as they are now ſpoken vnto vs, but thei wil not heare the (ſayth the lorde) no more wyll we. Thou ſhalt crye vpon them for to turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr ſynnes (as ſome ther be that crie vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs) but they wyll not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the (ſayth the Lorde)
<pb facs="tcp:184229:32"/> no more wyl not we. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhalte thou ſaye vnto them, as it may be now ſayd vnto vs. This is the people that neither heareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of the lord their god, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth his correction, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; trueth is cleane ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of theyr mouthes, as it is cleane gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For we be all aduouterers and a ſhrynkyng ſort,<note place="margin">Ierem, ix,</note> we bend our tongues like bowes to ſhote out lyes, as for the truth we maye not away wyth all to folowe it, for we go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one wickednes to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other, yea one muſt kepe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, no man may ſafely truſt his owne brother, for one bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder minethe another,<note place="margin">Mich, vii a,</note> and one neyghboure begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lethe another, yea one dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth wyth another, and
<pb facs="tcp:184229:33"/> we deale with no trueth, yea our tongues are lyke ſharpe arowes to ſpeake diſceipte. For although we heare and reade &amp; can ſay alſo that the lord lyueth &amp; is a rewarder of ſoch euyl &amp; wickednes, yet wyll we ſweare to deceyue.<note place="margin">The pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues for ſynnes</note> Although we do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that god hath ſcourged &amp; plaged vs wyth warres, peſtelence, derth, &amp; hunger for oure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet wyl we not repente, we wyl confeſſe alſo that the lord doeth ſende all theſe for our correction &amp; amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyfe, but yet we wyl not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue it. Neyther yet amend: And thee cauſe why is thys, that we are ſo pufte vp with pryde and ouerwhelmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crueltye and vnryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that wee wyll neyther heare nor ſe nor yet amend,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:33"/> for as it is wrytten whan va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyte and ydlenes getteth the ouer hand amonge the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men,<note place="margin">Pſalm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> al ar full of the vngodly,<note place="margin">Ierem. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for lyke as a net is full of byrdes, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ar their houſes full of that, whyche they haue gotten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> falſhed &amp; dyſceypte. And hereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth theyr great ſubſtaunce and riches, hereof ar they ſo fat &amp; ſo welthy and ar runne awaye from the lorde wyth ſhamefull blaſphemyes, for they mynyſter not the lawe, they make no ende of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles cauſe,<note place="margin">O ye Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ye ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites. Mic. iii, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they iudge not the poore according to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and ryght, ſhuld not I pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh theſe thinges (ſayth the lord) ſhuld not I be auenged of al ſoch people as theſe be,<note place="margin">☜</note> horrible &amp; greuous thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ar done in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes
<pb facs="tcp:184229:34"/> teach falſely &amp; the prieſtes fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low them &amp; my people hathe pleaſure therein, what wyll come therof at the laſt, vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye deſtructyon yf we do not repent, for there is nothyng now to turne the wrathe of god fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs but onely repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce &amp; amendment of lyfe, for the lord hathe bleſſed vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoch a plenteous bleſſing &amp; ſo longe time (not onely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frutes of the erth) but alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his knowledge of his holi &amp; ſacred word of lyfe by hys preachers &amp; we do not amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that it ſemethe vnto me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the tyme is at hand that the lorde wyll punyſſhe ſo ſore that we ſhall not be able to abyde it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. Cor. i, c</note> For al the promiſes of god are yet in hym, and ar Amen in hym, to the prayſe of God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:34"/>
            <p>And ſurely the promyſe of God is to ſend and geue his people al thinges neceſſary &amp; plentuouſly. Yf than, when they haue it, they be vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke full for it, &amp; become vayne &amp; wycked in theyr ymaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as we are nowe in thys Realme. Euen lyke vnto the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Nume, xi pſa lxxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i, Corin, x,</note> what muſt folow, verely euen as it dyd vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rede the places, for what ſhuld the lorde do that he hath not done for vs. He hath geuen vs a land that is ſo plenteous that we lack no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinge that we can deſyre or aſke, yea not onely that, but alſo he hath put almooſt all realmes &amp; nations in feare &amp; drede of vs, the which ſhuld be a great cauſe that we ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be thankeful vnto him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it. But it is ſo come to
<pb facs="tcp:184229:35"/> paſſe now (the more is the py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie) that euery one wyll ſaye that my wyſdom,<note place="margin">deu. viii, d</note> my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth my forecaſte &amp; polycye haue done it &amp; brought it to paſſe, and as it were, reioyce in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and not prayſe God for it which onely is worthy of all prayſe for all thinges. Wherfore yf we wyl not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hede in tyme,<note place="margin">The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chaſſinge hym, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſe ſtandeth ſtyf as a Lyon. pro, xxviii. a Le, xxvi, b, pro, xxviii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it wyll come to paſſe, that as all Realmes &amp; nacions haue ſtand in awe &amp; fled before vs, euen ſo wyll the lord make vs afrayd and flee before al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; to tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne our backes towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; not our faces wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede is.</p>
            <p>Nowe yf it come thus to paſſe, ſurely it is oure ſynnes &amp; wickednes that is the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe therof, for it is thus writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten alſo by the prophet Iob, for the wickednes &amp; ſynne of the people god maketh an y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:35"/>
            <p>Hereby do I proue &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke that it is ſo lyke to come to paſſe as I haue ſayde, for thus is it wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of god.<note place="margin">Eccleſia. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iere. xxvii Danie. iiii</note> Becauſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous dealinge, wronge blaſphemies, &amp; diuers decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, a realme ſhal be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one people to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other. Now truely here be the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes that I do feare &amp; ſuſpect in vs very moche, for ſurely in my iudgement there was neuer more wronge amonge men tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is now in theſe oure dayes, neuer more blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of gods holy name tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe, neuer more deceyptes than is now, yea I thinke &amp; beleue verely that ther was nothing ſo moch in the tyme of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (before the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell was knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) as there is now, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people had
<pb facs="tcp:184229:36"/> ſome feare of GOD before their eyes, but nowe there is no feare of god before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all,<note place="margin">iiii, Eſdr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. viii. t.</note> but as it is wrytten, they haue taken lybertie, deſpyſed the hyeſt, thought ſcorne of hys lawe, and forſaken hys wayes, moreouer they haue trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe hys righteous and ſayd in their hartes that ther is no god, yea, and that wittingly.<note place="margin">O Lorde who wyll geue my head wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ynough &amp; a well of teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for mine eyes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might wepe nigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and day for the ſlaughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. &amp;c. Iere. ix. a</note> O lord who wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not lament to heare &amp; ſee this, that thee people doo ſo cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to their know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, yea, &amp; alſo cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed by profeſſion in theyr Baptyſme to theyr onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; redemer, who is ſo mercyefull a God that he is ready too forgeue euery one that turneth vnto hym vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedly wyth al theyr hart.
<pb facs="tcp:184229:36"/> Wherfore turne you, turne you vnto the Lord, O wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore wyl you periſhe in your ſynnes, O turne you &amp; take now the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl of the lord which ſayth by hys prophet Eſaye. Waſſhe you,<note place="margin">Eſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. i. c.</note> make you cleane, putte away your euyll thoughtes frome you, ceaſſe from doynge euyl and vyolence, and learne to doo right, and apply your ſelues wholy to equytie and ryght, delyuer thee oppreſſed, helpe the fatherles to hys ryghte, let the wydowes complaynt come before you, &amp; ſee that ye now walke in the wayes and ſtatutes of the lord god of Iſrael, for he is a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous god, &amp; rewardeth euery one accordinge to his worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.<note place="margin">Pſalm v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For god is a righteous Iudge (ſayth the Prophet)
<pb facs="tcp:184229:37"/> and he is euer threatening yf men wyl not turne, he hathe whet his ſwerd, he hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his bowe &amp; made it redy, he hath prepared him the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of death &amp; ordeyned his arowes to deſtroye.</p>
            <p>O take theſe warninges of the Lordes owne mouth (I beſeche you) ſeynge that ye wyl not take none of hys ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">As for the warnynge of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets they take it but for wynde Ierem. v. b</note> remember Lots two ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in law, that ſhuld haue maried his two dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, whan Lot gaue theym warninge to flee the wrathe of god (which came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cytie &amp; thee people therein) they toke it but for a ſporte,<note place="margin">Gen. xix, c</note> and wolde not. Wherefore they were deſtroyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee wycked: Euen ſo you yf ye take the wordes of god but for a ſport and wyll not bee
<pb facs="tcp:184229:37"/> warned of your ſynnes and wyckednes in tyme, ye ſhall ſureli periſh in dede. Althou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe god do reſerue you here in this worlde (to what ende or purpoſe I can not tel) yet ſhall you be ſure of eternall conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacyon in the worlde to come by hys promys.</p>
            <p>But lord who beleueth our preachinges or geuethe any credence vnto our ſayinges,<note place="margin">Eſa. liii. a Iohn. xi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Roma .x. e</note> 
               <note place="margin">Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſawe thee boldnes of Peter and Iohn &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtode y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were vnlearned &amp; laye men they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled, Actu. iiii b</note> for we ar dyſpiſed among al people, becauſe we be vnlear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned (as they call learnynge) of the vnyuerſytes, for they do not conſyder, neyther yet know (or els they wyll not) what is learnynge, neyther what is vnderſtandynge as thee holye ghoſte doeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyne it in the holy ſcriptures, for thus doeth the wyſdom of god proue learnynge and
<pb facs="tcp:184229:38"/> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng in the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of God, fyrſte thus ſayth Iob,<note place="margin">Iob xxviii c.</note> to feare the lord is wyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, &amp; to forſake euyl is vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng. Lo, here the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes doeth approue &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge learning whiche is good and accepted in thee ſight of god, is to be a feard to offend god. And to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil is ryght vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>din<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge (ſayth he), alſo Dauid in the Pſalmes doeth ſaye,<note place="margin">Pſal, cx, c</note> the feare of the lord is the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; a good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding haue al they that do therafter, yea the prayſe of it endureth for euer ſayth he, lo here doeth Dauid prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe well doyng &amp; not wel ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only.<note place="margin">Prou, ix, v</note> Alſo Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith in the boke of the prouerbes the feare of the lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:184229:38"/> of holy thinges is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. And thus do I approue by theſe ſcriptures y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chefe lerning which befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re god is accepted &amp; alowed, is, to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures of god, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to feare him &amp; to depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al euil, &amp; ſo to walke in his way al our life lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ende. But the world doth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low him to be lerned that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay many wordes, &amp; ſet it out with many painted ſcole ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, flattering &amp; deceiuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; although the life be as farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life, as white fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> black, &amp; light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> darcknes. But I ſay (&amp; the holy goſt doth alſo affirme it to be trewe) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath al the learninge that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the vniuerſites (yf it
<pb facs="tcp:184229:39"/> were poſſible for one man to haue it) he hathe no promyſe of god to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of god a ryght and to be ſaued,<note place="margin">Wycked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decerne not the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that is ryght, but they that ſeke after the Lorde, diſcuſſe al thinges, Pro, xxviii</note> excepte he departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyl &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynew with wel doyng vnto the ende.</p>
            <p>I haue not ſaid this to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe learnyng, but to put al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce that they ſhulde not truſt ſo moche in learnyng that they ſhuld lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue wel doing &amp; to think lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning ſufficient into ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For learninge is good &amp; the gift of the holy ghoſt, geuen to the glorye of god &amp; profyt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s yf it be accompanyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vertue &amp; godly lyuynge. But yf it be accompanyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, vayne glorye, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, enuye, hatred, malyce, and gorgeous apparel vaine
<pb facs="tcp:184229:39"/> paſtymes &amp; all thynges that pertayne to a worldly &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal lyfe not ſekynge no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfycation of the fleſh. What doeth it profyte, verelye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but procure goddes wrathe too that perſon that hathe it, for ſo moche as he doeth abuſe thee good gyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of god geuen vnto hym to ſet forthe hys glory and prayſe in the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and doeth ſeke but his own pryuate welthe prayſe and vayne glory onely. And thys is the ſpyrytuall wyckednes in heauenlye thynges that Saynte Paule ſpeakethe of to thee Epheſyans, thee .vi.<note place="margin">Eph. vi, b</note> Chapter.</p>
            <p>But as it is ſayde before, thee worlde doethe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe oure ſayinges, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it, neyther wyll they fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="tcp:184229:40"/> it, becauſe we do not ſet it forth with ſclole learnyng and paynted eloquence. Yet notwythſtanding we ſpeake the trueth &amp; tel the people of their ſinnes, becauſe we wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not haue them peryſhe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned, and becauſe we do ſo and walk not with them in the ſame exceſſe of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ote as they do, in eating and drynckyng, in ſportyng and playing, in the luſtes of thee fleſh,<note place="margin">We ar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyled &amp; yet we bleſſe, we ar per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted &amp; ſuffer it, we ar euyl ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, &amp; yet we pray .i. cor. iiii, b.</note> in wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes &amp; in al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ryatous liuyng. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſpeake they euyl of vs &amp; care not what thei ſay of vs, but as S. Peter ſayth, they ſhal geue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes vnto hym (for it) that is redy to Iudge bothe quycke and the deade.</p>
            <p>But Saynte Paul was not aſhamed to confeſſe and ſaye: my brethren, whan I
<pb facs="tcp:184229:40"/> came vnto you,<note place="margin">i, Cor, ii, a.</note> I came not in gloriouſnes of wordes or of wyſdom, ſhewynge vnto you the teſtimony of god, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhewed I my ſelf that I knew any thing among you ſaue Ieſus chriſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that was crucified, and I was amonge you in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and in feare and in moch trymblynge. And my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; my preachynges were not wythe intyſynge wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of mannes wyſdome, but in ſhewynge of thee ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte and power that youre fayth ſhuld not ſtande in the wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men, but in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of god, ſayth he.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo I my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do not ſhew you the wordes of god with the wiſdom of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in the power and wythe the ſpyryte of the Lorde, as
<pb facs="tcp:184229:41"/> my conſcyence is wytnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god, to thee helynge of you, too thee knowledge of god and ſaluacyon of youre ſoules. Nether do I ſeke the praiſe of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of god (who ought onli to haue al praiſe) neither do I ſeke youres, but you, neyther wolde I haue your faith ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath moch learning &amp; his lyfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge agreyng to the ſame, but let your fayth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god &amp; his word, and let hym that fearethe god &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from euyll be youre ſhew token to folow after. For it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Mat. vii b</note> Not al they that ſaye mayſter maiſter, or lord lorde ſhal enter into the kyngdome of heauen, but all thoſe that do the wil of hym that is in heauen (ſayth chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte) manye ſhall ſaye vnto
<pb facs="tcp:184229:41"/> me, Lord Lord haue we not prophecied in thy name, haue we not caſt out deuyls in thi name, haue we not done ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny great miracles in thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. And then wyl I acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth chriſt) that I neuer knew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore depart from me ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquitie.</p>
            <p>Lo, note here I pray you what wyl be ſayd to the euil &amp; wicked doers, all thoughe they haue neuer ſo moch lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge, neuer ſo moch wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuer ſo moch eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yea, &amp; though they haue neuer ſo many ſpiritual gyftes of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, yf they be euyll &amp; wycked doers, it wyll be ſayde vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, depart from me ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquitie, Therfore yf any man wyll be of chriſt, he muſte be a newe creature,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:42"/> as for olde thinges he muſt caſt them away, &amp; as the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet ſayth,<note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. xviii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> caſt away all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlyneſſe that ye haue done and make you a new harte &amp; a new ſpyrite, neuertheles al thinges are of God whyche hath reconcyled vs vnto him ſelf by Ieſus chriſt, and hath geuen me thys mynde to tell vnto you thys attonemente, that God was in Chriſt and made agreemente betwene the world and hym ſelf, and imputed not theyr ſynnes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theym, whan ſoeuer they repent and turne from them, and therefore hath bounde me nowe in conſcyence to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye thee ſame vnto you in wrytinge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">We are not as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ar why the chop &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of god, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of purenes &amp; out of god in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of God ſo ſpeake we in Chriſte. ii. Cor, i. d</note>Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> am I a meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in the rowme of chriſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as though god dyd beſech you
<pb facs="tcp:184229:42"/> thorow me, ſo pray I you in Chriſtes ſteade that ye be at one wyth God, for he hathe made him to be ſynne for vs, whyche knew no ſynne, that we by that meanes ſhulde be that ryghteouſnes which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god is alowed. I as an helper therfore doo exhorte you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye receaue not the gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of God in vayne,<note place="margin">Eſa. xlix b</note> for he ſaith I haue heard the in the tyme excepted, &amp; in the day of ſaluacion haue I ſuccoured the, behold (ſayth he) nowe is thee excepted tyme, nowe is the daye of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is thee daye and tyme of ſaluatyon?) verelye euen whan ſoeuer god offreth to anye man repentaunce, by thee openynge of hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto hym, that he maye ſee hys owne Synnes,
<pb facs="tcp:184229:43"/> and the great mercy of God offred vnto him in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu, than I ſay, is the day and tyme of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon offered, yf he be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receaue it &amp; inbrace it with teares for hys ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Wherfore my welbeloued brethren, be it knowen vnto you that the lord is not ſlack to fulfyl his promiſe, as ſom men counteth hym &amp; ſayeth, tuſhe, ſeing that the dayes of puniſhment are ſo ſlack in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, al the prophecies ar of none effect. I tel you therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thus ſayth the Lord god. The dayes are euen at hand that euery thing which hath ben prophecied ſhalbe fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.<note place="margin">Ezec. xii. d</note> Ther ſhal no vyſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in vayne, neither any prophecye fayle among the chyldren of Iſrael, for it is I the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:184229:43"/> that ſpake it, &amp; what ſoeuer I the Lord ſpake, it ſhall be performed in hys tyme &amp; not be ſlack in comminge. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for the loue and tender mercye of God, yf ye beleue thys to be trew (or haue any ſparckle of loue or feare in you) be ye warned in tyme, &amp; be diligente that ye maye be found before him in peace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out ſpot and vndefyled, and count the longe ſuffering of the Lord your ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And nowe to all you that wyll be warned of theſe ſayinges &amp; wryting in dede, &amp; do knowe it before hand, beware, leaſt ye be alſo pluckt awaye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the errour of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and fal from your owne ſtedfaſtnes, but grow in gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; in the knowledge of our Lorde and Sauiour Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:184229:44"/> Chriſte. And take the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle of the holy ghoſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayth:<note place="margin">Eſay. iii. b</note> Away awaye, get you out from thence &amp; touch no vncleane thing. God out from among ſoch, &amp; be clene all ye that beare thee veſſels of the Lorde. And agayn S. Paul ſayeth: Come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge theym and ſeperate your ſelues (ſayth the Lord) and touch no vncleane thing and ſo wyll I receaue you (ſayth the Lord) and be your father and ye ſhalbe my ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and daughters, ſaith the almighty Lord, vnto whom wyth the ſonne and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt be all honoure and glorye. AMEN.</p>
            <p>The Lorde of all mercy ſende vs Preachers wythe power (that is to ſaye) trew expoundes of the worde of
<pb facs="tcp:184229:44"/> God, and ſpeakers to thee hartes of men, and delyuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scrybes, Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis, Hypocrytes, and all falſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; teachers.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>¶ Geue al prayſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God onely, for he is worthy, and none but he, G.C.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at London in Paules Church yearde, at the ſygne of the ſtarre, By Thomas Raynalde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184229:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
